Fritz von Unruh Papers
Fritz von Unruh Papers
1922-1964
Unruh, Fritz von, 1885-1970.
0.5 linear ft.
Papers of the German dramatist, novelist, poet. Collection includes twenty-one items of incoming correspondence (1962-1961); the manuscript for the novel, Ein Traum, and five smaller manuscripts; and memorabilia, including clippings, photographs, and reviews.
148713
Biographical History
Fritz von Unruh (1885-1970) was a German army officer and later anti-war expressionist playwright, poet and novelist.
Unruh was born in Koblenz on 10 May 1885 to an aristocratic German family, the son of a general who was a lifelong friend of General Hindenburg. After attending military school at Plon in Schleswig-Holstein, he became a professional soldier in the cavalry and during World War I was an officer, but he later became one of Germany's leading voices of anti-militarism between the world wars.
First in the play Offiziere (1912) and then in works including Der Opfergang (1916) and The Way of Sacrifice (1919, written near Verdun), he questioned the old values of patriotic honor. His confinement in an asylum before the end of the war may have saved him from a battlefield death. His antimilitarist views were further elaborated in the plays Ein Geschlect (1918) and Platz (1920).
During the 1920s he played a wider role in German public affairs. Active in politics, he was a co-founder of the Republican Party, which he represented in the Reichstag, but as Hitler rose to power his position in Germany became less secure. He emigrated to France, where he contributed to the anti-Nazi press, then to the United States in 1940 where he settled in New York. He wrote at least one novel in English during this period ( The End is Not Yet, 1947). In 1957 he published an autobiography, Der Sohn des Generals (The Son of the General), and shortly thereafter he and his wife moved to Atlantic City, New Jersey (1960). Two years later he lost his manuscripts, artwork and personal belongings in a coastal storm and the looting that followed.
Fritz von Unruh died in Diez, Germany on 28 Nov 1970 at the age of 85.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Fritz von Unruh Papers comprises manuscripts, memorabilia, some incoming correspondence, and a few of the author's writings in printed form.
Correspondence contains 21 letters addressed to Unruh. Correspondents include Ernst Feder, Andre von Gronicka, Luc Durtain, and H. V. Kaltenborn. An index of correspondents appears at the end of this inventory.
Manuscripts include a 210-page manuscript of Ein Traum, a novel written in 1959-1960. The manuscripts leaves were numbered in pencil by the library during processing. There is also an annotated carbon typescript of Meine Begegnung mit Trotzki, undated, with a one-page preface, a two-page summary, and revisions that were not incorporated into the text as it appeared in the Sämtliche Werke. The manuscript is incomplete. There are also five smaller manuscripts.
Memorabilia includes clippings about Fritz von Unruh, photographs, a wax imprint of his personal seal, and two typescript carbons (1927 and undated) of reviews of Unruh's work.
A small file of Writings completes the collection. Most significant is a copy of Flügel der Nike with the author's notes and corrections to the text on six of its pages. A larger collection of Unruh's books, most of them inscribed by the author to Syracuse University, is housed in the Rare Books collection.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged chronologically; all others series are arranged alphabetically.
Subject and Genre Headings
Unruh, Fritz von, 1885-1970.; Unruh, Fritz von, 1885-1970. Traum.; Dramatists, German.; German literature -- 20th century.; Novelists, German.; Poets, German.; Book reviews.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Manuscripts for publication.; Photographs.; Dramatists.; Novelists.; Poets.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Fritz von Unruh, 1964.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - 1952, 1960, 1961, undated (Box 1)
- Manuscripts
  - Dietrich, undated; handwritten, one page (Box 1)
  - Frieden oder Untergang, undated; typescript copy, 3 pp. (Box 1)
  - Meine Begegnung mit Trotzki, undated; annotated typescript copy, 145 pp. (Box 1)
  - Romain Rolland, Oct 1943; typescript, 2 pp. (Box 1)
  - Ein Traum, 1959-1960; handwritten, 220 pp. (Box 1)
  - Und wenn die Welt voll Teufel wär!, 21 Apr 1960; annotated typescript copy, 6 pp. (Box 1)
  - Weh dem Volk, das Seiner Seele frevelt!, undated; annotated typescript, 6 pp. (Box 1)
- Memorabilia
  - Advertising fliers for Unruh's works, 1952-1964; undated; 15 items, including duplicates (Box 1)
  - Articles about Unruh, 1960-1962; 6 items (Box 1)
  - Clippings about Unruh, 1941-1953; 1958-1964 (Box 1)
  - Clippings about miscellaneous topics, 1948-1963 (Box 1)
  - Photographs, undated; 4 items (Box 1)
  - Reviews by Unruh of various books, 1957-1961 (Box 1)
  - Reviews of works by Unruh
    - "Buhne und Politik. Gedanken zu Unruh's 'Bonaparte' " von Gertrud Baumer. Abschrift, Vossische Zeitung, Berlin., 2 Mar 1927; typescript, 5 pp. (Box 1)
    - "On Die Heilige," by George Gustav Wieszner, undated; typescript, 2 pp. (Box 1)
  - Seal, personal (Box 1)
  - Wrapper that accompanied the material to Syracuse, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous printed material, 1961-1964; undated (Box 1)
- Writings
  - Entscheiden wir uns für den Frieden so wird Frieden sein!, 1960; 16 pp, inscribed on the cover to Syracuse University (Box 1)
  - Flügel der Nike (Frankfurt-am-Main, Frankfurter Societäts-Druckerie), 1925; 403 pp, includes six pages with author's notes and corrections; inscribed on the flyleaf to Syracuse University (Box 1)
  - Die Lebendigen rufe ich, 1962; 27 pp, inscribed on the title page to Syracuse University (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous newspaper articles, 1922-1951; 3 items (Box 1)
  - Sport und Politik: ein Appell an die Jugend in aller Welt, 1961; 16 pp, inscribed on the cover to Syracuse University (Box 1)